Guide to the Chaffee family papers, 1826-[ca. 1937], 1988.
Chaffee family papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Chaffee family papers, 1826-[ca. 1937], 1988.
3889
Chaffee family.
6.9 cubic ft.
Correspondence, printed material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Chaffee family letters; book of remedies; a copy of LOVE LIES BLEEDING by Helen Smith Jordan, a book in which some of the letters are reproduced; a booklet "Civil War Letters Received by the Family of E.F. Chaffee, Attica, N.Y. 1861-1865," also by Helen Smith Jordan; and "Musings and Memories," by Henry Chaffee Abell, 1988.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Thomas Chaffee came from England in about 1633 and settled in Hingham, Massachusetts. He had two sons, Nathan and Joseph. Joseph married Ann Martin in 1669, and they had nine children. One son, James, was married twice and had 20 children. Most of them moved to western New York, many settling near Attica. The second son, Nathan, son of James' first wife, Berea Hayden, married Priscilla Wedge of Woodstock, Connecticut, and they later moved to Brookfield, Massachusetts. Their son William married Rachel Rice in 1807. In 1817 William and Rachel moved to a farm south of Attica. The couple had nine children (excluding one who died in Massachusetts). At least one child, Edward Franklin Chaffee, remained in or near Attica his entire life. He taught at and was a principal of the Attica Union School, and helped to pass legislation to make it a free school.
Edward Chaffee also wrote local history articles for the local press. He married Harriette E. Jones in 1845, and they had six (surviving) children: Mary Abigail, William Franklin, Harriette Emeline, Eliza Rosette, Katie Evangeline, and Nellie Josephine.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Chaffee family letters; book of remedies; a copy of LOVE LIES BLEEDING by Helen Smith Jordan, a book in which some of the letters are reproduced; a booklet "Civil War Letters Received by the Family of E.F. Chaffee, Attica, N.Y. 1861-1865," also by Helen Smith Jordan; and "Musings and Memories," by Henry Chaffee Abell, 1988.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Chaffee family.; Abell, Henry Chaffee.; Abell, Mary Abigail Chaffee, 1846-1875.; Chaffee, Ann Martin.; Chaffee, Berea Hayden.; Chaffee, Edward Franklin.; Chaffee, Eliza Rosetta.; Chaffee, Harriette Emeline.; Chaffee, James.; Chaffee, Katie Evangeline.; Chaffee, Nathan.; Chaffee, Nellie Josephine.; Chaffee, Priscilla Wedge.; Chaffee, Rachel Rice.; Chaffee, Thomas.; Chaffee, William Franklin.; Chaffee, William.; Jordan, Helen Smith.; Jordan, Helen Smith.; Attica Union School.
Subjects:
Schools.; Farmers.; Teachers.
Places:
Attica (N.Y.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Form and Genre Terms:
Genealogies.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Letters
Subseries Ia: Loose Letters in Chronological Order
Subseries Ib: Group Letters
Subseries Ic: Typed copies
Series II. Documents, Newspapers and Manuscripts
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Letters
  - Subseries Ia: Loose Letters in Chronological Order
    - Descriptions and lists of letters (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1841-1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1861-1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1867-1888 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1889-1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1911-1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters with envelopes, 1931-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Loose letters, 1851,1861-1864 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter, printed item, bone rings carved by a soldier in the Civil War (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Loose letters, 1965-1867 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Loose letters, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Loose letters, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Loose letters, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Loose letters, 1879-1886 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Loose letters, 1887-1907 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Loose letters, 1909-1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries Ib: Grouped letters
    - Letters from Robert, 1912-1918 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Helen, WWI (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Faith Jones about death, 1850s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Civil War letters to Edward Chaffee, 1860s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Edward Jones, Harriet Chaffee letter (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Edward Chaffee soldier letter, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Chaffee letters, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Union Village, Vermont (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Old Adams letter, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letters to Kate and Eliza, 1871-1879 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Description of letters (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous letters (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Copies of miscellaneous letters (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letters to or from Nell Smith (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - William Jones to William Chaffee (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous letters (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letters to Nell Smith, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Sigrid's students' letters (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Handwritten copies of letters from Mary's children, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Emma, etc. not decipherable (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Free Methodist letters (Mary), clippings (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Cornell Correspondence with Helen Jordan about donated letters (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Stanford Press letters about publication, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Nell Chaffee letters, undates (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Nell's notes and baby mementos (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Nell Chaffee letters, 1845-1900 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Nell Chaffee letters, 1901-1915 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Nell Chaffee letters, 1918-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Nell Chaffee letters, 1939-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Chaffee letters, 1864-1878 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chaffee letters, 1869-1880 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chaffee letters, 1856-1871 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chaffee letters, 1874-1883 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chaffee letters, 1884-1885 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letters to Kate and Nell, 1879-1898 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Letters from Nellie to Robert, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letters from Helen Smith, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Letters from Helen Smith, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Letters from Edward Jones, 1895-1919 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Henry's report cards (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Letters from Olafson attic, 1913-1935 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Letters from Nell to Emma, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Mary Chaffee Abell to family, 1860-1875 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Smith family wallet and notebook (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - To Nell from Helen, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Empty envelopes (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Harriet and Helen, from Nancy (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Joseph Smith to Nellie, 1893, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Nancy to Bob, 1872-1890 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Eliza to husband, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous Smith family, 1889-1922 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Edward Smith letters to parents, 1914-1919 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Emma to Nell. Includes rattle from snake, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Henry Abell to Helen Jordan, 1954-1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Robert Smith letters, 1914-1944 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Smith family letter (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - Letters to Chaffees with copies, 1840-1860 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Smith family papers, 1840-1858 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subseries Ic: Typed copies
    - Smith family letters, 1826-1854 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Kate's letters to Joseph, with summaries, 1881-1885 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Letters to Helen (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous, 1860-1903 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Copies organized in chronological order, 1826-1915 (Box 5)
    - Copies and typed letters (Box 8)
- Series II: Documents, Newspapers and Manuscripts
  - "The Truth About Mary Abigail" publication packet, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Poem by Mary, Chaffee information (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Two photographs (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Free methodist materials (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Aumni reunion materials (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Manuscript for newspaper, Edward Chaffee? (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Poetry (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Story of an African American woman (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Legal deeds (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Katie Chaffee's papers from desk (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Edward Chaffee "Recollection of a New England Trip" (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Family Chart, photographs (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Certificates, licenses (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Musings and Memories" by Henry C. Abell (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Sander's Reader, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Story of Reverend Musket (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - A. Stevens school materials (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Central New York Genealogical Society "Tree Talks" (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Attica history newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, with wallet (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
  - Newspaper clippings in scrapbook album (Box 6)
  - 7 rolled documents (Box 6)
  - Nell's diaries, up to 1922 (Box 7)
  - Negatives and papers for Love Lies Bleeding (Box 9)
  - Love Lies Bleeding (Box 9)
  - Typed Civil War letters (Box 9)
  - Love Lies Bleeding prints (Box 88)